Hello everyone, welcome back to English.
My name is Marco and I'm Erica and
we're bringing you the third part of our
suspense series of new guy in town.
That's right. What's going to happen today?
Well, I don't know. There's still
so many things that could happen.
This guy is kind of weird, right?
You know, is he a vampire?
Like, what's going on?
Yeah, and I would like to think all
of our listeners for contributing and
sending out their ideas of what
they think happens in this third part.
Yeah, I especially like the
story about the rabbits.
Yeah, the rabbit. That was a good one.
As promised, we took the idea of one
of our listeners and created the dialogue
around it and this time it was
a contribution of Babar Dawan.
Yeah, he gave us a
great idea of the dialogue.
Exactly, he gave us a really good idea,
so thank you Babar and this one is for you.
In this dialogue, we're going to be
looking at some hospitality vocabulary.
Yeah, some phrases you can use when
you welcome someone to your house.
All right, well, we've
got some language to
preview, so let's turn
now to vocabulary preview.
Very vocabulary preview.
On vocabulary preview,
we have the word appetite.
Appetite.
So, Erica, tell us about appetite.
When you have an appetite, you're hungry
or you have a desire to eat food, right?
All right, so you can
have a big appetite, a small
appetite, really hungry,
a little bit hungry.
Okay, let's look at our next word, poison.
Poison.
So, poison could be a noun or a verb?
Exactly.
So, when you poison someone, you put something
in their food or maybe in their drink
that makes them really sick
and maybe even make them die.
Okay, so two poisons somebody.
Yeah, and the noun is actually the thing
that you put inside the food or drink.
So, usually poison is some
sort of chemical substance.
Yes, snakes, for example, have poison.
Yeah, in their teeth, right?
So, if you get bitten by a
snake, you'll get poisoned.
You'll get poisoned.
All right, so let's
take a look at our
dialogue for the first
time and see why we are
talking about poison, and we'll come
back and explain some great words.
Let's make yourselves at home.
Well, let me take your coats.
Dinner's almost ready.
I hope you brought your appetite.
Well, house is lovely, I'm on.
Very interesting decor, very gothic.
I think it's amazing.
Oh, you have such good taste, Armand.
I'm thinking of redecorating my house.
Maybe you could give me a few pointers.
It would be my pleasure.
Please have a seat.
Can I offer you a glass of wine?
We would love some.
Here you are, a very special merlot,
brought directly from my home country.
It has a unique ingredient, which gives
it a pleasant aroma and a superior flavor.
Mm, it's delicious.
It's a bit bitter for my taste,
almost tastes like, like, Ellen.
Ellen?
Are you okay?
Did she pass out?
Yeah.
I hope you didn't poison
her drink too much.
You ruined our meal.
[LAUGHTER]
OK, so that was unexpected.
No, Lois, can you believe it?
Apparently, Lois is helping Armand.
I know.
Maybe she's a vampire.
All right, well, I really wonder
what's going to happen next.
We'll see what happens next.
But now, let's take a look at some of
the language in language takeaway.
Language takeaway.
All right, so we have a couple
of words in language takeaway.
Today, let's start off with pointers.
Pointers.
So to give somebody pointers,
you give them some suggestions.
Suggestions or tips?
Exactly.
All right, so suggestions or tips.
Let's listen to some examples
of how you would use it.
Example one.
I want to dance salsa better.
Can you give me a few pointers?
Example two.
I need some pointers on
how to be a better manager.
Example three.
Let me give you a few pointers
so you can pass your exam.
All right, so pointers, it's clear now.
Let's take a look at our next
word, aroma aroma aroma.
This is a nice round word, aroma.
Well, this word makes
you sound really educated.
Yeah, yeah.
Basically, it means smell.
Yep, so you could say, for example,
this coffee has a great aroma.
Or maybe this perfume has
the aroma of roses and lavender.
Nice.
Okay, let's take a look
at our next word, bitter.
Bitter.
B-I-T-T-E-R, bitter.
Okay, bitter.
So bitter is the opposite of sweets.
Of sweet.
So it's always hard to
describe taste, isn't it?
Yeah.
But maybe we can say a
few foods that are bitter.
Okay.
So chocolate when it
has no sugar is bitter.
Okay.
Or for example, coffee
without any sugar is also bitter.
Yeah, and sometimes red
wine can be quite bitter.
Mm-hmm.
So bitter.
Okay, and now let's take a
look at our last word, pass out.
Pass out.
It seems kind of easy, pass and out.
Yep.
But it means something different.
Yeah, when you put them
together, what does it mean?
It means fate or become unconscious.
Okay.
So imagine someone,
you know, they're standing
up and then suddenly they start to move
around and then fall over to the ground.
Okay, pass out.
Yes.
This usually happens when
you get really, really drunk.
Maybe sometimes also when maybe
you're pregnant, you might pass out.
Right.
Okay.
To lose consciousness.
Yes.
Marco and I have a couple of
examples of this word for you.
Example one.
I drank so much last night that I
passed out at my friend's house.
Example two.
She was standing in the sun too long,
so she passed out right in front of me.
Example three.
My sister passes out
whenever she sees blood.
All right.
So let's listen to her dialogue again now.
We're going to slow it
down a little bit and you'll
be able to hear these
words that we just have.
Please make yourselves at home.
Let me take your coats.
Dinner is almost ready.
I hope you brought your appetite.
Your house is lovely, I'm on.
Very interesting decor, very gothic.
I think it's amazing.
You have such good taste, Arman.
I'm thinking of redecorating my house.
Maybe you could give me a few pointers.
It would be my pleasure.
Please have a seat.
Can I offer you a glass of wine?
We would love some.
Here you are, a very special Merlot
brought directly from my home country.
It has a unique ingredient, which gives
it a pleasant aroma and superior flavor.
Mmm.
It's delicious.
It's a bit bitter for my taste,
almost tastes like, like, Ellen.
Ellen, are you okay?
Did she pass out?
I hope that you didn't
poison her drink too much.
You'll ruin our meal.
Alright, so interesting story.
Yes.
We have some great
phrases that we've used
here, so let's take a look
at them in fluency builder.
Fluency builder.
We've got four
phrases for you that are
great to use when you
want to welcome someone
into your house or into
your office or anywhere, really.
Exactly.
So, why don't we take
a look at the first one?
Please make yourselves at home.
Please make yourself at home.
So this is a very common phrase
when you invite somebody to your house.
Yeah.
You always use this phrase.
It's like, make yourself
comfortable, relax, sit down.
Yeah.
Don't worry about it.
My house is your house.
Exactly.
Please make yourself at home.
Okay.
Good one.
Usually people arrive
to a party or to a
dinner with jackets,
coats, scarves, all that stuff.
So this next phrase is really handy.
Let me take your coats.
So that means give me your
coats and I'll put them in the closet.
Right.
Let me take your coats.
And then a good host would
always offer a drink, right?
Exactly.
Water or in this case, wine.
So they would say, can I
offer you a glass of wine?
Or sometimes you could
say, can I offer you a glass?
Can I offer you something to drink?
Yeah.
So, can I offer you a glass of wine?
Can I offer you a glass of wine?
You offer me a glass of wine.
I say, yeah, sure.
I'll take a glass of wine.
All right.
Let me use our next phrase.
Here you are.
Exactly.
It doesn't mean that you are here.
No.
It's saying to someone, here it is.
Take it.
Yes.
Right.
You know what?
This is a really, really great phrase.
A lot of people who
are learning English
don't say this, but it's
really common, really natural.
And if you use it,
it'll sound really great.
Here you are.
And you can use this anytime
you give someone something.
Right.
Somebody a pen or a pencil, a notebook.
Here you are.
Here it is.
Yeah.
Okay.
Great words.
So let's listen to our dialogue one
more time, and then we'll come back.
Please, make yourselves at home.
Let me take your coats.
Dinner's almost ready.
I hope you brought your appetite.
Your house is lovely, I'm on.
Very interesting deckle.
Very gothic.
I think it's amazing.
Oh, you have such good taste, Armand.
I'm thinking of redecorating my house.
Maybe you could give me a few pointers.
It would be my pleasure.
Please have a seat.
Can I offer you a glass of wine?
We would love some.
And here you are.
A very special merlot, brought
directly from my home country.
It has a unique ingredient, which gives
it a pleasant aroma and a superior flavor.
Mm.
It's delicious.
It's a bit bitter for my
taste, almost tastes like Ellen.
Ellen, are you okay?
Did she pass out?
Yeah.
I hope you didn't poison
her drink too much.
You'll ruin our meal.
Okay, so Armand is a pretty good host.
He offered them a merlot.
Yeah, which is the type of wine.
A type of wine.
And this is really interesting
because there are many types of wines.
Yes.
Do you know any?
All right.
So give us some pointers here.
Merlot is probably like the
most common red wine, right?
And Merlot is actually the grape variety.
The grape variety.
For it all.
It's called the wine speak.
Wow, varietal.
Yeah.
Well, right now, I'm really liking to
drink Tempernillo, which is a Spanish wine.
Tempernillo.
Yeah.
Really?
And is that also the type of grape?
Yes.
Oh, nice.
Usually we would say red
wine or white wine, right?
The varieties, depending on the
grapes, is what gives them their names.
So we also have a couple of other
like maybe you have a Chardonnay.
Mm-hmm.
White wine.
You have a cover nay, seven young.
Red wine.
Red wine again.
And my personal favorite is a carbonaire.
Oh, yeah.
That's a nice wine.
That's a nice one.
Yeah.
And it's not very common anymore.
Apparently the grape isn't growing
very well in France anymore or in Spain.
So from what I understand, it's only in
Chile and Argentina, but it's a real good.
Argentina makes really good common here.
Yeah.
But you know who else makes good wine?
Who?
Canadians.
Really?
Yes.
Canadian wine.
Yeah.
You almost never find it outside of Canada,
but there is one region in the western part
of the country that
makes really, really good
wines, especially some nice pino
noirs and some good white wines.
Okanagan Valley.
Check it out.
Nice.
Yeah.
All right.
Well, what about in your
country do you produce
any wine or maybe
any other type of drink?
Yes.
Any countries have their own types
of drinks, so we want to know about it.
Tell us.
And many countries have different traditions
to be hospitable, to be welcoming.
Exactly.
Yeah.
That's a good one.
So visit our website, www.EnglishPod.com.
Leave all your comments.
Tell us about how you
welcome people into your house.
All right.
And we'll be there to answer them.
But we got to go now.
Until next time.
Bye.
[MUSIC]